Klingon added by zrajm of Klingonska Akademien.
http://klingonska.org/
= Klingon, Ç...È = backtranslation
(...) = line from script (not in DVD subtitle)
(This is an emergency! We have suffered -)
???
ÇHelp us! [...]È
Ç"To be or not to be."È
ÇFather.È
ÇWe are returning now.È
ÇFind ...!È
???
We've lost gravity!
ÇGravity has been disabled!È
???
ÇWhat are your orders?È
ÇWhere are they?È
ÇEmergency!È
FIXME: I hear  (two syllables) on desktop; or  on laptop
We are betrayed!
ÇThey have definitely tricked us!È
ÇIntruder!È
Find Chang.
ÇFind Chang now!È
FIXME: I hear something like
or
ÇWho the hell are you?!È
FIXME sounds more like  or sm.th.
ÇHelp us!È
FIXME: sound like ÇgoquahÈ
ÇWhat the hell is happening?È
Restoring auxiliary gravity.
ÇRe-enabling vessel gravity.È
ÇAlert sick bay!È
???
ÇPick him up.È
ÇDon't touch him.È
ÇCome with me!È
Attack them now, while we still can!
Attack or be slaves in their world.
We can take whole by force, what they propose to divide.
???
ÜQaplaH Üpla'Ý pe'vIlÝ or: ÜQapla' ghobe' laH'a'Ý
ÇYou don't seem to grasp our situation, General.È
War is obsolete, General, as we are in danger of becoming.
ÇWar is obsolete, but soon we are becoming obsolete too.È
Better to die on our feet than live on our knees.
That wasn't what my father wanted.
ÇÜÑtaH paghÝ ÜDaH wa'noSÝ fired intentionally at Chronos One.È
(Seqram's speculation: ÜbaHpa'Ý Qo'noS Qo'noS wa'Daq baHta' ['entepray])
FIXME: Chang continues to speak, overlap with translator
Again. Again!
???
Ç*@$%È
FIXME: 2(?) more Klingon lines from the court audience
ÇKeep moving!È
ÇMove!È
ÇGet up!È
ÇKeep moving!È
ÇMove!È
ÇHurry up! Hurry up!È
ÇKeep moving!È
FIXME: more sentences
???
This is listening post Morska.
What ship is that? Over.
We must respond personally.
-
We am thy freighter Ursva.
Six weeks out of Kronos.
We is condemning food, things and supplies.
Don't catch any bugs!
They were beamed aboard a Federation starship.
ÇThe were beamed away.È
I could trace...
ÇI could trace for you...È
ÇThey have escaped.È
Escaped.
Kirk cannot know the location
of the peace conference.
Are you sure?
Will you take that chance?
ÇHelmsman!È
-  ÇSir!È
Helmsman, make course to intercept Enterprise.
-
What's she doing?
ÇWhy is she going there?È
ÇRely on us!È
FIXME - 2 lines
Protect the Chancellor!