Klingon added by zrajm of Klingonska Akademien.
http://klingonska.org/
= Klingon, «...» = backtranslation
(...) = line from script (not in DVD subtitle)
Stardate 9521.6.
Captain's Log, U.S.S. Excelsior.
Hikaru Sulu commanding.
After three years,
I've concluded my first assignment
as master of this vessel,
cataloguing gaseous planetary
anomalies in Beta Quadrant.
We're heading home
under full impulse power.
I am pleased to report
that ship and crew have functioned well.
According to this, we've completed
our survey of the entire sector.
I have an energy wave
at 240 degrees mark 6 port, sir.
Visual.
My God.
Shields. Shields!
She's not answering her helm.
Starboard thruster.
Turn her into the wave.
Aye.
Quarter impulse power.
Damage report.
Checking all systems, Captain.
Don't tell me
that was any meteor shower.
Negative, sir.
The subspace shockwave
originated at bearing 3-2-3 mark 75.
Location...
It's Praxis, sir. It's a Klingon moon.
Praxis is their key
energy production facility.
Send to Klingon High Command.
"This is Excelsior,
a Federation starship.
"We have monitored
a large explosion in your sector.
"Do you require assistance?"
- Aye, sir.
- Mr. Valtane, any more data?
Yes, sir. I've confirmed
the location of Praxis, but...
What is it?
I cannot confirm the existence of Praxis.
Onscreen.
Magnify.
Computer enhancement.
- Praxis?
- What's left of it, sir.
Captain,
I'm getting a message from Praxis.
Let's have it.
(This is an emergency! We have suffered -)
???
«Help us! [...]»
This is Brigadier Kerla
speaking for the High Command.
There has been an incident on Praxis.
However, everything is under control.
We have no need for assistance.
Obey treaty stipulations
and remain outside the neutral zone.
This transmission ends now.
"An incident"?
- Do we report this, sir?
- Are you kidding?
What are we doing here?
Maybe they're throwing us
a retirement party.
- That suits me. I just bought a boat.
- This had better be good.
I'm supposed to be chairing a seminar
at the Academy.
Captain, isn't this just for top brass?
If we're all here, where's Sulu?
Captain Sulu. On assignment.
Where's Spock?
This briefing is classified.
Ladies and gentlemen, the CinC.
As you were.
To break this information down
succinctly,
the Klingon Empire
has roughly 50 years of life left to it.
For full details,
I'm turning this briefing over
to the Federation's special envoy.
Good morning.
Two months ago, a Federation starship
monitored an explosion
on the Klingon moon Praxis.
We believe it was caused
by over-mining
and insufficient safety precautions.
The moon's decimation means
the deadly pollution of their ozone.
They will have depleted
their supply of oxygen
in approximately 50 Earth years.
Due to their enormous military budget,
the Klingon economy does not have
the resources
with which to combat this catastrophe.
Last month, at the behest
of the Vulcan ambassador,
I opened a dialogue with Gorkon,
Chancellor of the Klingon High Council.
He proposes to commence negotiations
at once.
Negotiations for what?
The dismantling of our space stations
and starbases along the neutral zone,
an end to almost 70 years
of unremitting hostility,
which the Klingons can no longer afford.
Bill, are we talking
about mothballing the Starfleet?
Well, I'm sure that our exploration
and scientific programs
- would be unaffected, Captain, but...
- I must protest.
To offer Klingons safe haven
within Federation space is suicide.
Klingons would become
the alien trash of the galaxy,
and if we dismantle the fleet,
we'd be defenseless
before an aggressive species
with a foothold on our territory.
The opportunity here
is to bring them to their knees.
Then we'll be in a far better position
to dictate terms.
Sir?
Captain Kirk.
The Klingons
have never been trustworthy.
I'm forced to agree
with Admiral Cartwright.
This is a terrifying idea.
It is imperative that we act now
to support the Gorkon initiative
lest more conservative elements
persuade his empire
that it is better to attempt
a military solution and die fighting.
You, Captain Kirk,
are to be our first olive branch.
We have volunteered to rendezvous
with the Klingon vessel
which is bringing Chancellor Gorkon
to Earth
and to escort him safely
through Federation space.
Me?
Well, there are Klingons who feel
the same way about the peace treaty
as yourself and Admiral Cartwright,
but they'll think twice about attacking
the Enterprise under your command.
I have personally vouched for you
in this matter, Captain.
You have personally vouched?
You will extend Chancellor Gorkon
full diplomatic courtesy, Captain Kirk.
But a full ambassador
would be better equipped...
If there's no further business,
I wish you and your crew Godspeed.
Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
I remind you, this meeting is classified.
I don't know whether
to congratulate you or not, Jim.
I wouldn't.
We volunteered?
There is an old Vulcan proverb,
"Only Nixon could go to China."
How could you vouch for me?
That's arrogant presumption.
My father requested
that I open negotiations...
I know your father's the Vulcan
ambassador, for heaven's sake,
but you know how I feel about this.
They're animals.
Jim, there is an historic opportunity
here.
Don't believe them. Don't trust them.
- They are dying.
- Let them die.
Has it occurred to you that this crew
is due to stand down in three months?
We've done our bit for king and country.
You should have trusted me.
Control, this is SD-103,
approach to spacedock. Over.
SD-103, you are clear
to deliver Captain Kirk and party
to NCC-1701 Alpha. Over.
Captain on the Bridge.
- As you were, Lieutenant...
- Valeris, sir.
We were told that you needed
a helmsman, so I volunteered.
Lieutenant, it is agreeable
to see you again.
Lieutenant was the first Vulcan
to be graduated
- at the top of her class at the academy.
- You must be very proud.
I don't believe so, sir.
She's a Vulcan, all right.
Let's get this over with.
Departure stations.
- Scotty.
- Aye, sir?
Did you find the engine room?
Right where I left it, sir.
Standby. Uhura, get me the dockmaster.
Control tower reading, sir.
Control, this is Enterprise
requesting permission to depart.
This is Control, Enterprise.
Permission to depart granted.
Thirty seconds for port gates.
Clear all moorings.
Awaiting port gates from this mark.
All moorings clear.
Aft thrusters.
Thank you, Lieutenant.
One-quarter impulse power.
Captain, may I remind you
that regulations specify thrusters
only while in spacedock?
Jim?
You heard the order, Lieutenant.
Aye, sir.
Captain's Log, Stardate 9522.6.
I've never trusted Klingons,
and I never will.
I could never forgive them
for the death of my boy.
It seems to me our mission
to escort the Chancellor
of the Klingon High Council
to a peace summit
is problematic at best.
Spock says this could be
an historic occasion,
and I'd like to believe him,
but how on earth can history
get past people like me?
Sorry.
You could have knocked.
We are almost at the rendezvous, sir.
I thought that you would like to know.
Right.
Permission to speak freely, sir.
It is an honor to serve with you.
You piloted well
out of spacedock, Lieutenant.
I've always wanted to try that, sir.
You've done well, Valeris.
As your sponsor at the academy,
I have followed your career
with satisfaction,
and as a Vulcan,
you've exceeded my expectations.
I do not understand this representation.
It is a depiction
from ancient Earth mythology,
the expulsion from Paradise.
Why keep it in your quarters?
It is a reminder to me
that all things end.
It is of endings that I wish to speak.
Sir, I address you as a kindred intellect.
Do you not recognize
that a turning point has been reached
in the affairs of the Federation?
History is replete
with turning points, Lieutenant.
- You must have faith.
- Faith?
That the universe
will unfold as it should.
- But is that logical? Surely we must...
- Logic, logic and logic.
Logic is the beginning
of wisdom, Valeris,
not the end.
This will be my final voyage onboard
this vessel as a member of her crew.
Nature abhors a vacuum.
I intend you to replace me.
I could only succeed you, sir.
Now hear this. All officers to the Bridge.
Klingon battle cruiser off the port bow.
All officers to the Bridge.
Captain on the Bridge.
Shall we raise our shields, Captain?
Never been this close.
The Chancellor is undoubtedly awaiting
our signal.
- Uhura, hailing frequencies.
- Aye, sir.
Right standard rudder.
Bring us alongside.
Z plus 5 degrees.
Channel is open, Captain.
This is the Starship Enterprise,
Captain James T. Kirk commanding.
This is Kronos One.
I am Chancellor Gorkon.
Chancellor, we've been ordered
to escort you
through Federation space
to your meeting on Earth.
Thank you, Captain.
Would you and your party
care to dine this evening
aboard the Enterprise with my officers,
as guests
of the United Federation of Planets?
We would be delighted to accept
your gracious invitation.
We'll make arrangements to have you
beamed aboard at 1930 hours.
I shall look forward to that.
- Well, I hope you're happy.
- Captain,
there is a supply
of Romulan ale aboard.
It might make the evening
pass more smoothly.
Officer thinking, Lieutenant.
Guess who's coming to dinner.
Energize.
- Chancellor Gorkon.
- Captain Kirk.
May I present Captain Spock,
whom I believe you know.
Captain, face to face at last.
- You have my thanks.
- Chancellor.
Gentlemen,
this is my daughter Azetbur,
my military adviser, Brigadier Kerla,
and this is General Chang,
my chief of staff.
I have so wanted to meet you, Captain.
I'm not sure how to take that.
Sincere admiration, Kirk.
From one warrior to another.
Right.
This way.
I think you might enjoy a brief tour.
- They all look alike.
- What about that smell?
You know only top-of-the-line models
can even talk...
You men have work?
- Yes, ma'am.
Then snap to it.
I offer a toast.
"The undiscover'd country,"
the future.
- "The undiscover'd country."
Hamlet, Act III, Scene 1.
You've not experienced Shakespeare
until you have read him
in the original Klingon.
«"To be or not to be."»
Captain Kirk,
I thought Romulan ale was illegal.
One of the advantages
of being 1,000 light-years
from Federation Headquarters.
To you, Chancellor Gorkon,
one of the architects of our future.
- Chancellor.
«Father.»
Perhaps we are looking
at something of that future here.
Tell me, Captain Kirk,
would you be willing
to give up Starfleet?
I believe the Captain feels
that Starfleet's mission
has always been one of peace.
Far be it for me
to dispute my first officer,
but Starfleet has always been
at the fore...
Captain, there's no need
to mince words.
In space, all warriors are cold warriors.
General, are you fond of
Shakespeare?
We do believe all planets
have a sovereign claim
to inalienable human rights.
Inalien?
If you could only hear yourselves.
"Human rights."
Why, the very name is racist.
The Federation is no more
than a "Homo Sapiens Only" club.
Present company excepted, of course.
In any case,
we know where this is leading.
- The annihilation of our culture.
- That's not true.
- No?
- No.
"To be, or not to be."
That is the question which preoccupies
our people, Captain Kirk.
- We need breathing room.
- Earth, Hitler, 1938.
I beg your pardon?
Well...
I see we have a long way to go.
We must do this again sometime.
You don't trust me, do you?
I don't blame you.
If there is to be a brave new world,
our generation is going
to have the hardest time living in it.
Captain Spock.
Chancellor.
- Madam.
- Captain.
Well, most kind.
"Parting is such sweet sorrow," Captain.
Have we not
"heard the chimes at midnight"?
«We are returning now.»
Thank God.
Did you see the way they ate?
Terrible table manners.
I doubt that our own behavior
will distinguish us
in the annals of diplomacy.
I'm going to sleep this off.
Please let me know if there's some
other way we can screw up tonight.
I'm going to go find
a pot of black coffee.
The Enterprise hosted
Chancellor Gorkon and company
to dinner last night.
Our manners weren't exactly
Emily Post.
Note to the galley,
Romulan ale no longer to be served
at diplomatic functions.
Captain Kirk, will you please
join me on the Bridge?
Captain Kirk?
- Captain.
- What is it?
I find this curious.
Spock, I'm really tired.
We are reading an enormous amount
of neutron radiation.
Where?
Strangely enough,
it appears to be emanating from us.
The Enterprise?
Valeris, do you know anything
about a radiation surge?
Sir?
Chekov?
Only the size of my head.
I know what you mean.
- What's happened?
- We have fired on the Chancellor's ship.
Torpedo Room, please confirm.
Have we fired?
...0-6...
- Uhura, monitor.
- Aye, sir.
Direct hit.
Confirmed, sir.
«Find ...!»
???
We've lost gravity!
«Gravity has been disabled!»
???
«What are your orders?»
«Where are they?»
«Emergency!»
FIXME: I hear  (two syllables) on desktop; or  on laptop
We are betrayed!
«They have definitely tricked us!»
This is the Bridge. Do you read?
Do you read?
Torpedo bay,
did we fire those torpedoes?
Negative, Captain.
According to inventory,
we're still fully loaded.
«Intruder!»
Find Chang.
«Find Chang now!»
FIXME: I hear something like
or
Unable to confirm or deny
firing of two photon torpedoes.
- Hailing frequencies.
- Aye, sir.
Kronos One, this is Enterprise.
Do you read? Over.
Repeat. Kronos One...
«Who the hell are you?!»
FIXME sounds more like  or sm.th.
«Help us!»
FIXME: sound like «goquah»
«What the hell is happening?»
It's very hard to make out, Captain.
There's been some weapons firing
and a lot of shouting.
She is still listing.
She's spinning out of control.
Restoring auxiliary gravity.
«Re-enabling vessel gravity.»
Have you not a shred
of decency in you, Kirk?
We come in peace,
and you blatantly defile that peace.
For that,
I shall blow you out of the stars.
- We haven't fired.
- Captain.
According to our databanks,
we have, twice.
Captain, they're coming about.
- They're preparing to fire.
- Shields up, Captain?
- Captain, our shields.
- Signal our surrender.
- Captain?
We surrender!
- This is Enterprise. We surrender.
- If they fire at us
- with our shields down...
- I repeat.
- We surrender.
- ...we will not be able to respond.
Repeat. Enterprise surrenders.
- Are we firing torpedoes?
- I wish I knew.
Well, it sure looks like it.
I'm going aboard.
Spock, you have the conn.
I am responsible
for involving you in this. I will go.
No, I'll go. You'll be responsible
for getting me out of this.
We'll not be the instigators
of full-scale war
on the eve of universal peace.
I'm going, too. They may need a doctor.
- Perhaps you're right.
- Uhura, tell them we're coming,
and tell them we're unarmed.
Aye, sir.
Have you lost your mind?
I give you my word,
I don't understand what has happened.
We're here to help.
Follow me.
«Alert sick bay!»
???
- Chancellor Gorkon.
- My God.
- What has happened here?
- You dare to feign ignorance?
- What happened?
- With a direct torpedo hit,
you crippled
our entire gravitational field,
and two of your Starfleet crew
beamed aboard wearing magnetic boots
and did this.
Aren't you carrying a surgeon?
We were until this disgrace.
Well, then for God sakes, man,
let me help.
I've got a pulse. We can move him.
I'm gonna need some light.
Can we get him up on this table?
«Pick him up.»
???
«Don't touch him.»
Hold him. Hold him while I stabilize him.
I said hold him.
Sweet Jesus.
- Can you...
- Jim, I don't even know his anatomy.
- His wounds are not closing.
- He's killing him!
He's gone into
some kind of damned arrest.
Come on, damn it! Come on!
He's not responding.
Don't let it end this way, Captain.
Under article number 184
of your interstellar law,
I'm placing you under arrest.
You are charged with assassinating
our Chancellor of the High Council.
He tried to save him.
«Come with me!»
They've been arrested.
Mr. Spock, we've got to do something.
I assume command of this ship
as of 0230 hours.
Commander Uhura,
please notify Starfleet Headquarters.
Tell them precisely
what has taken place
- and request instructions.
- Aye, sir.
We cannot allow them to be taken back
to Kronos as prisoners.
What do you suggest, Lieutenant?
Opening fire will not retrieve them,
and an armed conflict is precisely
what the Captain wished to avoid.
We will be able to follow
the Captain's movements.
- How did you achieve this, sir?
- Time is precious, Lieutenant.
We must endeavor to piece together
what happened here tonight.
According to our databank,
this ship fired those torpedoes.
No way.
I sympathize, Mr. Scott,
but we need evidence.
Please accompany me.
And if we cannot
piece together what happened?
- What then, sir?
- In that case, Mr. Chekov,
it resides in the purview
of the diplomats.
The Chancellor of the High Council
is dead!
The result of an unprovoked attack
while he travelled to see you
under a flag of truce,
on a mission of peace.
Captain Kirk was legally arrested
for the crime.
May I remind you that he and Dr McCoy
boarded Kronos One
of their own free will?
None of these facts are in dispute,
Mr. President.
I have ordered a full-scale investigation.
- In the meantime...
- In the meantime,
we expect the Federation to abide
by the articles of interstellar law,
which you claim to cherish.
Kirk and Dr McCoy will stand trial
for the assassination
of Chancellor Gorkon.
Out of the question.
Ambassador Sarek,
there must be some way
to extradite these men.
Mr. President, I share a measure
of personal responsibility in this matter,
but I am obliged to confirm
my esteemed colleague's
legal interpretation.
What is the position
of the Romulan government,
Ambassador Nanclus?
I must concur with my colleagues.
But you can't possibly believe
that James Kirk assassinated
the Chancellor of the High Council.
Mr. President,
I don't know what to believe.
I'm waiting for your answer, sir.
This president is not above the law.
Report back at once. Do you copy?
At once.
Enterprise to report back on the double.
Do you read? At once.
We're to report back at once.
We cannot abandon
Captain Kirk and Dr McCoy.
Of course not.
Four hundred years ago
on the planet Earth,
workers who felt their livelihood
threatened by automation
flung their wooden shoes called "sabot"
into the machines to stop them.
Hence the word "sabotage."
We are experiencing
technical malfunction.
All backup systems inoperative.
Excellent. I mean, too bad.
Mr. President,
I've been named Chancellor
by the High Council
in my father's place.
Madam Chancellor,
you have my sincerest condolences
on your recent loss.
I want to assure you
that this shameful deed will not...
Mr. President, let us come to the point.
You want this conference
to go forward, and so did my father.
I will attend in one week
on one condition.
We will not extradite the prisoners,
and you will make no attempt
to rescue them in a military operation.
We would consider any such attempt
an act of war.
We hope you'll be our guest
here on Earth.
After recent events, you will understand
if I say I prefer a neutral site,
and in the interests of security,
let us keep the location secret for now.
As you wish, Madam Chancellor.
Attack them now, while we still can!
Attack or be slaves in their world.
We can take whole by force, what they propose to divide.
???
‹QaplaH ‹pla'› pe'vIl› or: ‹Qapla' ghobe' laH'a'›
«You don't seem to grasp our situation, General.»
War is obsolete, General, as we are in danger of becoming.
«War is obsolete, but soon we are becoming obsolete too.»
Better to die on our feet than live on our knees.
That wasn't what my father wanted.
Your father was killed
for what he wanted.
The peace process will go forward.
Kirk...
Kirk will pay for my father's death.
- Kirk! Kirk!
- Kirk! Kirk! Kirk! Kirk!
It's a damn show trial.
- Kirk! Kirk!
«‹—taH pagh› ‹DaH wa'noS› fired intentionally at Chronos One.»
(Seqram's speculation: ‹baHpa'› Qo'noS Qo'noS wa'Daq baHta' ['entepray])
The Enterprise fired on Kronos One
without provocation.
FIXME: Chang continues to speak, overlap with translator
The Chancellor and his advisers...
...having been lulled
into a false sense of security
by an invitation to a state dinner
aboard Captain Kirk's vessel
at precisely 1930 hours
that same evening.
Call your first witness.
After the first shot,
we lost our gravitational field.
I found myself weightless
and unable to function.
Then two Starfleet crewmen
came walking towards me.
But perhaps they merely wore
Starfleet uniforms.
That remark is purely speculative.
I move that it be stricken.
Colonel Worf,
we are interested in facts, not theories.
If the gravitational unit
was not functioning,
how could these men be walking?
They appeared to be wearing
magnetic boots.
Gravity boots.
Dr McCoy,
would you be so good as to tell me,
what is your current medical status?
Aside from a touch of arthritis,
I'd say pretty good.
You have a singular wit, Doctor.
For 27 years, I've been ship surgeon
aboard the U.S.S. Enterprise.
In three months, I stand down.
You know, I believe that you consumed
a rather generous amount
of Romulan ale in the officers' mess
on the night in question.
Am I right, Doctor?
- Objection!
- Sustained.
We all did. All of us.
- That doesn't mean...
- Was Chancellor Gorkon alive
when you first examined him?
- Barely.
- Now be careful, Doctor.
Have you ever, in your past,
saved patients as barely alive as he?
I didn't have the medical knowledge
I needed for Klingon anatomy.
- I see.
- You were there.
You say you are due for retirement.
May I ask, do your hands shake?
- Objection!
- I was nervous.
No.
You were incompetent.
You were incompetent!
Whether deliberately or as a result
of age combined with drink,
- the court will have to determine.
- My God, man! I tried to save him!
I tried to save him.
I was desperate to save him.
He was the last best hope
in the universe for peace.
The witness is excused.
There we have it, citizens.
We have finally established
the particulars of the crime,
and now we come to the architect
of this tragic affair,
James Tiberius Kirk.
What would
your favorite author say, Captain?
"Let us sit upon the ground
"and tell sad stories
of the death of kings."
Tell us your sad story, Kirk.
Tell us that you planned to take revenge
for the death of your son.
- That's not true.
- Objection!
Captain Kirk has not been identified
as the assassin.
Sustained.
I offer into the record
this excerpt
from the Captain's personal log.
I've never trusted Klingons,
and I never will.
I have never been able to forgive them
for the death of my boy.
Again. Again!
???
I've never trusted Klingons,
and I never will.
I have never been able to forgive them
for the death of my boy.
«*@$%»
Are those your words?
Those words were spoken by me.
Objection!
My client's political views
are not on trial here.
On the contrary!
Captain Kirk's views and motives
are indeed
at the very heart of the matter.
This officer's record
shows him to be an insubordinate,
unprincipled,
career-minded opportunist,
with a history of violating
the chain of command
whenever it suited him!
Continue.
Indeed, the record shows
that Captain Kirk
once held the rank of Admiral,
and that Admiral Kirk was broken
for taking matters into his own hands
in defiance of regulations of the law.
Do you deny being demoted
for these charges?
Don't wait for the translation!
Answer me now!
I cannot deny it.
- You were demoted?
- Yes.
- For insubordination?
- On occasion, I have disobeyed orders.
And were you obeying
or disobeying orders
when you arranged the assassination
of Chancellor Gorkon?
I didn't know about the assassination
until we boarded the ship.
You still deny the Enterprise
fired on Kronos One?
- Well...
- Your Honors, please!
And you still deny your men beamed
aboard and shot the Chancellor?
Objection!
I cannot confirm or deny actions
I did not witness.
Captain Kirk,
are you aware
that as the captain of a starship,
you are required to be responsible
for the actions of your men?
I am.
And if it should be proved
that members of your crew
did, in fact,
carry out such an assassination...
Jim, they're setting us up.
Your Honors...
Do not answer!
Captain Kirk,
you will answer the question.
???
FIXME: 2(?) more Klingon lines from the court audience
As captain,
I am responsible for the conduct
of the crew under my command.
Your Honors, the State rests.
Send to Commander Enterprise.
"We stand ready to assist you.
Captain Sulu, U.S.S. Excelsior. "
It is the determination of this court
that the prisoners are guilty as charged.
I wish to note for the record
that the evidence against my clients
is entirely circumstantial.
I beg the court to consider this
when pronouncing its sentence.
So noted.
Captain James T. Kirk,
Dr Leonard McCoy,
in the interest of fostering amity
for the forthcoming peace talks,
the sentence of death is commuted.
It is the judgment of this court
that, without possibility of reprieve
or parole,
you be taken from this place
to the dilithium mines
on the penal asteroid of Rura Penthe,
there to spend
the rest of your natural lives.
Rura Penthe?
Known throughout the galaxy
as the aliens' graveyard.
Better to kill them now
and get it over with.
Lieutenant, the torpedo hit
once again, please.
Hold.
It is Enterprise.
- We fired.
- That is not possible.
All weapons visually accounted for, sir.
An ancestor of mine maintained
that if you eliminate the impossible,
whatever remains, however improbable,
must be the truth.
What exactly does that mean?
It means that if we cannot
have fired those torpedoes,
someone else did.
Well, they did not fire on themselves,
and there were no other ships present.
There was
an enormous neutron energy surge.
Not from us!
A neutron surge that big
could only be produced by another ship.
Kronos One?
Too far away.
Very near us. Possibly beneath us.
If there were a ship beneath us,
the Klingons would have seen her.
Would they?
- A bird-of-prey.
Cloaked?
A bird-of-prey cannot fire
when she's cloaked.
All things being equal, Mr. Scott,
I would agree.
However, things are not equal.
This one can.
We must inform Starfleet Command.
Inform them of what,
a new weapon that is invisible?
Raving lunatics,
that's what they'll call us.
They'll say that we're so desperate
to exonerate the Captain
that we'll say anything.
And they would be correct.
We have no evidence,
only a theory
which happens to fit the facts.
Assuming you're right, Mr. Spock,
why would they fire
on their own president?
Indeed.
This ship will be searched
from bow to stern.
Lieutenant Valeris, you'll be in charge.
- Aye, sir.
- I do not understand.
If there was a ship underneath us,
surely the assassins
beamed aboard from that vessel,
not Enterprise.
You're forgetting something,
Mr. Chekov.
According to our databanks,
this ship fired those torpedoes.
If we did, the killers are here.
If we did not,
whoever altered the databanks is here.
In either case,
what we are looking for is here.
What are we looking for, sir?
Lieutenant?
Two pairs of gravity boots.
«Keep moving!»
«Move!»
«Get up!»
«Keep moving!»
This is the gulag Rura Penthe.
There is no stockade, no guard tower,
no electronic frontier.
Only a magnetic shield
prevents beaming.
Punishment means exile
from prison to the surface.
On the surface, nothing can survive.
Work well and you will be treated well.
Work badly and you will die.
«Keep moving!»
????
«Move!»
«Keep moving!»
«Hurry up! Hurry up!»
FIXME: more sentences
Oh, my God.
The universal translator's
been confiscated.
I'm sorry?
He's definitely on about something, Jim.
If this is your spot, we'll move on.
He wants your obedience
to the brotherhood of aliens.
- He's got it.
- And your coat.
I'm afraid not. Besides, it wouldn't fit.
Thanks.
This will help keep you warm.
I'm Martia.
You're Kirk and McCoy, I presume.
How'd you know that?
We don't get many
presidential assassins.
- We didn't kill Gorkon.
- Of course not,
- but there is a reward for your death.
- It figures.
We've been set up all along.
Somebody up there
wants you out of the way.
- Nothing in here.
- Nothing here.
- Any progress?
- None.
We have a crew of 300
turning their own quarters inside out,
but the killers may still be among them.
Surely they have disposed
of these boots by now.
Would it not have been logical
to have left them on Gorkon's ship?
Even logic must give way to physics.
Gravity had not been restored
by the time they escaped.
Without the boots,
they would have floated off
the Klingon transporter pads.
Why not simply vaporize them?
Like this?
At ease.
As you know, Commander Chekov,
no one can fire an unauthorized phaser
aboard a starship.
Suppose when they returned,
they threw the boots into the refuse.
I'm having the refuse searched.
If my surmise is correct,
those boots will cling
to the killers' necks
like a pair of Tiberian bats.
They could not
make their escape without them,
nor can they simply throw them
out the window for all to see.
- Those boots are here somewhere.
- Did someone fire off a phaser?
It's all right. It's nothing. It's nothing.
Mr. Spock, Starfleet is screaming for us
to return to port.
- Who fired that...
- Mr. Scott.
I understand you're having difficulty
with the warp drive.
How much time
do you require for repair?
There's nothing wrong
with the bloody thing.
Mr. Scott, if we return to spacedock,
the assassins will surely find a way
to dispose
of their incriminating footwear,
and we will never see
the Captain or Dr McCoy alive again.
- It could take weeks, sir.
- Thank you, Mr. Scott.
Valeris, please inform
Starfleet Command
- our warp drive is inoperative.
- A lie?
An error.
You understand we have lost all contact
with the Captain and Dr McCoy.
Yes. At the moment, they're surrounded
by a magnetic shield.
However, if I know the Captain,
by this time,
he is deep into planning his escape.
You got him, Jim!
You got him where you want him!
- You all right, Jim?
- I think so.
- They'll respect you now.
- That's a comfort.
- I was lucky that thing had knees.
- That was not his knee.
Not everybody keeps their genitals
in the same place, Captain.
Anything you want to tell me?
Bones, why don't you see
what you can do for him?
Let him know
we're not holding a grudge.
Suppose he's holding a grudge?
When whoever it is makes their move,
you won't be here to ask if he's the one.
- Do you want to get out of here?
- There's gotta be a way.
Three months before retirement.
What a way to finish.
- We're not finished.
- No? Speak for yourself.
One day, one night, Kobayashi Maru.
Bones, are you afraid of the future?
I believe that was the general idea
that I was trying to convey.
I don't mean this future.
- What is this, multiple choice?
- Some people are afraid
of what might happen.
I was terrified.
What terrified you, specifically?
No more neutral zone.
I was used to hating Klingons.
It never even occurred to me
to take Gorkon at his word.
Spock was right.
Try not to be too hard on yourself.
We all felt exactly the same.
No.
Somebody felt a lot worse.
I'm beginning to understand why.
Well, if you've got any bright ideas,
now's the time.
Time's the problem.
You and I are nothing.
But you heard the judge.
The peace conference is on again.
Whoever killed Gorkon is bound
to attempt another assassination.
Unless we can get out of here.
Kirk, it's me, Martia.
Listen, no one has ever escaped
from Rura Penthe.
- Except us.
- It is possible.
- I know how to get outside the shield.
- How do we fit in?
Getting outside the shield is easy,
but after that, it's up to you to get us
off the surface before we freeze.
Can you?
- It's possible.
- I can't make it alone,
and you're likeliest candidate
to come in this hellhole for months.
Candidate for what?
Go to lift seven in the morning
for mining duty.
I'll see you there. Don't disappoint me.
- What is it with you, anyway?
- Still think we're finished?
More than ever.
- I'm sorry to wake you, sir.
- What is it?
Starfleet urgently requests
any data we have
on the whereabouts of Enterprise.
What?
Well, apparently, they're refusing
to acknowledge signal
to return to spacedock, sir.
Signal Starfleet that we have no idea
location Enterprise.
Sir?
- You have hearing problems, mister?
- No, sir.
Klingon blood.
They must have walked through it
when it was floating
and tracked it back here.
This is the first evidence
which corroborates our theory.
Now we go to Starfleet.
Now we expand our search
to include uniforms.
All uniforms?
Take those out.
- Continue scanning.
- Nothing, sir.
Clear, sir.
Coming through. Coming through.
Computer well seven clear.
Nothing. Nothing.
Okay, let's see what we got.
Nothing. Nothing so far.
Sir! Sir!
???
- I think we've been had.
- No, you weren't, Doctor.
Get off at the first level.
Follow the gang into the mine.
They don't take girls.
You are Crewman Dax?
Yes, Commander. What is the problem?
Perhaps you know
Russian epic of Cinderella?
If shoe fits, wear it.
Mr. Chekov.
Watch me.
What kind of creature is this?
Last night, you two were...
Don't remind me.
Get in.
???
Come on. We don't have a lot of time.
Hurry.
Up there.
Come on, climb.
Here. You'll need these. Quickly!
Stay close.
There they are.
They're emerging
from the beaming shield.
- Mr. Scott, start your engines.
- Aye, aye, sir.
Mr. Chekov, set course for Rura Penthe.
Mr. Spock, Rura Penthe
is deep inside the Klingon frontier.
- If we are discovered...
- Quite correct, Mr. Chekov.
What is required now
is a feat of linguistic legerdemain
and a degree of intrepidity
before the Captain and Dr McCoy
freeze to death.
- Leave me. I'm finished.
- No!
Bones, I'm wearing a viridium patch
on my back.
Spock slapped it there
just before we went on Gorkon's ship.
- Why, that cunning little Vulcan.
- Come on. We're in the clear.
Now that we're outside the shield,
they'll be able to locate us
two sectors away.
If they're even looking for us.
This is listening post Morska.
What ship is that? Over.
We must respond personally.
-
A universal translator
would be recognized.
We am thy freighter Ursva.
Six weeks out of Kronos.
What is your destination? Over.
We is condemning food, things and supplies.
Don't catch any bugs!
Would you mind explaining
that little trick you do?
- I'm a chameloid.
- I've heard about you.
Shapeshifters.
- I thought you were mythical.
- Give a girl a chance, Captain.
- It takes a lot of effort.
- I don't doubt it.
Stop me if I'm wrong,
but do we have any way of knowing
whether this is the real you?
I thought I would assume
a pleasing shape.
We're outside the shield.
Now it's your turn, Captain.
If you say so.
Are you crazy?
She didn't need our help
getting anywhere.
Where'd you get
these convenient clothes?
Don't tell me that flare
is standard prison issue.
It's to let them know where we are.
Ask her what she's getting in return.
A full pardon,
which doesn't cover this.
An accident wasn't good enough.
Come on, Spock.
Good enough for one.
Two would have looked suspicious.
Killed while attempting escape.
Now that's convincing for both.
Surprise!
- Your friends are late.
- They'll be along.
- I can't believe I kissed you.
- Must have been your lifelong ambition.
Isn't it about time
you became something else?
I like it here.
Well, well, well.
What took you so long?
- Kill him. He's the one.
- Not me, you idiot. Him!
- No witnesses.
- Killed while trying to escape.
- Damn clever, if you ask me.
- It's a classic.
- That's what he wanted.
- Who? Who wanted us killed?
Since you're all going to die anyway,
why not tell you?
His name is...
Damn it to hell! Of all the... Son of a...
- Couldn't you have waited two seconds?
- Captain?
He was just about to explain
the whole thing.
You want to go back?
- Absolutely not!
- It's cold.
This is the Bridge.
We are still in Klingon space.
Deck 9, remain at battle stations.
They were beamed aboard a Federation starship.
«The were beamed away.»
I could trace...
«I could trace for you...»
«They have escaped.»
Escaped.
Kirk cannot know the location
of the peace conference.
Are you sure?
Will you take that chance?
«Helmsman!»
-  «Sir!»
Helmsman, make course to intercept Enterprise.
-
The Klingons have a new weapon,
a bird-of-prey that can fire
when cloaked.
- She torpedoed Gorkon's ship.
- So that's it.
Not entirely. I have reason to believe
that Gorkon's murderers
- are aboard this vessel.
- I have a thought about that.
Has the peace conference begun?
Who knows?
They're keeping the location secret.
- There's always something.
- Captain!
Mr. Spock! I found the missing uniforms
with the Klingon blood on them.
But the uniforms belong
to these two men,
Burke and Samno.
Not anymore.
Phaser on stun at close range.
First rule of assassination,
kill the assassins.
- Now we're back to square one.
- Can I talk to you?
I wonder why they weren't vaporized.
It would set off the alarm.
It's possible.
Now hear this. Now hear this.
Court reporter to sickbay.
Code Blue. Urgent.
Statements to be taken at once
from yeomen Burke and Samno.
Repeat. Court reporter to sickbay.
Code Blue. Urgent.
Statements to be taken.
Repeat. Statements to be taken
from yeomen Burke and Samno.
You have to shoot.
If you are logical, you have to shoot.
I do not want to.
What you want is irrelevant.
What you've chosen is at hand.
I'd just as soon you didn't.
The operation is over.
I did not fire. You cannot prove anything.
Yes, I can. At my trial,
my personal log was used against me.
How long did you wait outside
my quarters before I noticed you?
You knew?
I tried to tell you,
but you would not listen.
Neither of us was hearing
very well that night, Lieutenant.
There were things I tried to tell you
about having faith.
You have betrayed the Federation.
All of you.
And what do you think
you've been doing?
Saving Starfleet.
Klingons cannot be trusted.
Sir.
You said so yourself.
They killed your son.
Did you not wish Gorkon dead?
"Let them die," you said.
Did I misinterpret you?
And you were right.
They conspired with us
to assassinate their own chancellor.
How trustworthy can they be?
Klingons and Federation members
conspiring together?
Who is "us"?
Everyone who stands
to lose from peace.
- Names, Lieutenant.
- My comrades will make certain
all your ship-to-shore transmissions
are jammed.
Names, Lieutenant.
I do not remember.
A lie?
A choice.
Spock?
Admiral Cartwright.
From Starfleet?
Who else?
- General...
- ...Chang.
Who else?
- Romulan...
- ...Ambassador...
- ...Nanclus.
Where is the peace conference?
She does not know.
Then we're dead.
I've been dead before.
Contact Excelsior.
- She'll have the coordinates.
- I've already got him, sir.
Standing by, Captain Kirk.
Sulu!
You realize that by even talking to us,
you're violating regulations.
I'm sorry, Captain.
Your message is breaking up.
Bless you, Sulu.
Where is the peace conference?
They're going to attempt
another assassination.
The conference is at Camp Khitomer,
near the Romulan border.
I'm sending the exact coordinates
on a coded frequency.
I'm afraid
we're gonna need more than that.
There's a bird-of-prey
on the lookout for us,
and she can fire while cloaked.
Surely not.
Hold on.
How many of those things are there?
Come on, Lieutenant.
- Just the prototype.
- You hear that?
I'm getting underway now,
but we're now in Alpha Quadrant.
The chances of our reaching
the conference in time are slim.
When does this conference start?
According to my information, today.
Thank you, Captain Sulu.
Don't mention it, Captain Kirk.
Spock?
I prefer it dark.
Dining on ashes?
You were right.
It was arrogant presumption on my part
that got us into this situation.
You and the doctor
might have been killed.
The night is young.
You said it yourself. It was logical.
Peace is worth a few personal risks.
You're a great one for logic.
I'm a great one for rushing in
where angels fear to tread.
We're both extremists.
Reality is probably
somewhere in between.
I couldn't get past the death of my son.
I was prejudiced
by her accomplishments as a Vulcan.
Gorkon had to die before I understood
how prejudiced I was.
Is it possible that we two, you and I,
have grown so old and so inflexible
that we have outlived our usefulness?
Would that constitute a joke?
Don't crucify yourself.
It wasn't your fault.
I was responsible.
- For no actions but your own.
- That is not what you said at your trial.
That was as captain of the ship.
Human beings...
But, Captain, we both know
that I am not human.
Spock, you want to know something?
Everybody's human.
I find that remark insulting.
Come on. I need you.
Madam Chancellor,
members of the Diplomatic Corps,
honored guests,
the United Federation of Planets
welcomes you to Camp Khitomer.
She's out here somewhere.
But if she is cloaked...
Then all we have
is a neutron radiation surge,
and by the time we're close enough
to record it, we're ashes.
209.
206.
203.
- Close enough to beam down?
- Not yet, Captain. In two minutes. 158.
- Go to impulse power for Khitomer orbit.
- Aye, sir.
Let us redefine progress to mean
that just because we can do a thing,
it does not necessarily follow
that we must do that thing.
- Uhura?
- Nothing, Captain.
If she's here,
she's rigged for silent running.
Coming up on transporter range
in 57 seconds.
Transporter Room,
stand by to beam down.
...53...
...48 seconds.
...44...
I can see you, Kirk.
Chang.
Can you see me?
Now, be honest, Captain.
Warrior to warrior,
you do prefer it this way, don't you?
As it was meant to be.
No peace in our time.
"Once more unto the breach,
dear friends."
- This is fun.
- Reverse engines. All astern.
One and a half impulse power.
Back off! Back off!
What's she doing?
«Why is she going there?»
What's she waiting for?
Probably attempting to ascertain
why we are reversing,
wondering whether we detect her.
Incoming!
- In range?
- Not yet, sir.
Come on. Come on.
- She'll fly apart.
- Fly her apart, then!
Many speculated
about my father's motives.
There were those who said
he was an idealist.
Others said he had no choice.
If Praxis had not exploded,
then quite possibly his idealism
would not have found expression.
We are a proud race,
and we are here because
we intend to go on being proud.
- Go to auxiliary power!
- Auxiliary circuits destroyed, Captain.
"Tickle us, do we not laugh?
Prick us, do we not bleed?
"Wrong us,
"shall we not revenge?"
Gas.
Gas, Captain. Under impulse power,
she expends fuel like any other vessel.
We call it plasma,
but whatever the Klingon designation,
it is merely ionized gas.
Well, what about all
of that equipment we're carrying
to catalogue gaseous anomalies?
- Well, the thing's gotta have a tailpipe.
- Doctor, would you care to assist me
- in performing surgery on a torpedo?
- Fascinating.
Hard to starboard!
The proposed agenda is as follows.
The total evacuation of Kronos
has been calculated
within the 50-Earth-year time span.
Phase one, preparation for evacuation.
Come on, reach up!
Captain! She's packing quite a wallop!
Shields weakening!
Shields up. All right.
Now we've given them
something else to shoot at.
Aye, sir.
The game's afoot, huh?
- Excelsior's been hit.
- "Our revels now are ended," Kirk.
"Cry 'Havoc!'
and let slip the dogs of war."
Bones, where's my torpedo?
Bet you wish you'd stood in bed.
Emergency power!
Gravity control down!
Shields collapsing!
The key, please, Doctor. Time is short.
The hull has been compromised.
- I wonder how bad?
- Connect echobars.
...to discuss the report on phase two.
- Alter circuit "A."
- Sensor.
I propose that we commence
with the minutes of the preparation.
"I am constant as the northern star."
I'd give real money if he'd shut up.
- Plate, please.
- Plate.
...and assimilation will consume...
We've got a heartbeat.
The Klingon empire, the ecological...
- Key, please.
- Key.
Where's that damn torpedo?
She's ready, Jim. Lock and load.
Fire.
To be,
or not
to be.
Target that explosion and fire.
Fire.
As I imagine this work will occupy us
throughout most of the week,
it would be my hope
that the delegation
could return to their capitals
to implement the provisions
of phase one,
no later than the first of next month.
Scotty.
As you know, time is of the essence.
- Out of the way!
Mr. President!
Mr. President! Mr. President!
Kirk, Enterprise.
«Rely on us!»
FIXME - 2 lines
Protect the Chancellor!
- Arrest those men!
- Arrest yourself.
We've got a full confession.
Cartwright, just a minute.
What's happened?
What's the meaning of all of this?
It's about the future, Madam Chancellor.
Some people think the future
means the end of history.
Well, we haven't run out
of history quite yet.
Your father called the future
the undiscovered country.
People can be very frightened
of change.
You've restored my father's faith.
And you've restored my son's.
Once again, we've saved civilization
as we know it.
And the good news is,
they're not going to prosecute.
They might as well have prosecuted me.
I felt like Lieutenant Valeris.
Well, they don't arrest people
for having feelings.
And it's a good thing, too. If they did,
we'd all have to turn ourselves in.
Captain Kirk.
Captain Sulu.
As much to the crew of the Enterprise,
I owe you my thanks.
Nice to see you in action
one more time, Captain Kirk.
Take care.
By God, that's a big ship.
- Not so big as her captain, I think.
- So, this is goodbye.
I think it's about time
we got underway ourselves.
Captain, I have orders
from Starfleet Command.
We're to put back
to spacedock immediately
to be decommissioned.
If I were human,
I believe my response would be,
"Go to hell."
If I were human.
Course heading, Captain?
Second star to the right,
and straight on till morning.
Captain's Log, Stardate 9529.1.
This is the final cruise
of the Starship Enterprise
under my command.
This ship and her history will shortly
become the care of another crew.
To them and their posterity
will we commit our future.
They will continue the voyages
we have begun,
and journey to all
the undiscovered countries,
boldly going where no man...
Where no one
has gone before.